<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Bigquery on nanta - Data Engineering</title><link>https://nanta-data.dev/en/tags/bigquery/</link><description>Recent content in Bigquery on nanta - Data Engineering</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>© 2026 nanta</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nanta-data.dev/en/tags/bigquery/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>BigQuery Data Transfer + Airflow: Why We Create and Delete Transfers Every Batch</title><link>https://nanta-data.dev/en/posts/bigquery-data-transfer-airflow/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nanta-data.dev/en/posts/bigquery-data-transfer-airflow/</guid><description>We built a pipeline to load S3 mart tables into BigQuery using Data Transfer Service. During PoC, DTS scheduling was managed by GCP. For production, we moved it into Airflow — creating a transfer object each batch tick and deleting it after completion. User feedback drove improvements: multi-day lookback windows, concurrent execution quota management via slot pools, and empty source path detection through GCP logging API.</description></item><item><title>Why BigQuery Hangs in Superset: The gevent and gRPC Incompatibility</title><link>https://nanta-data.dev/en/posts/bigquery-bi-integration/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nanta-data.dev/en/posts/bigquery-bi-integration/</guid><description>We integrated BigQuery with both Redash and Superset for per-user BI access. Redash had a known schema browsing limitation. Superset hit a much worse problem — queries executed successfully on BigQuery but results never came back, blocking indefinitely. The root cause: gunicorn&amp;rsquo;s gevent worker monkey-patches Python&amp;rsquo;s threading primitives, which deadlocks gRPC calls inside the BigQuery SDK. Switching the worker type to gthread resolved it. We contributed a docs fix upstream.</description></item></channel></rss>