<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Airflow on nanta - Data Engineering</title><link>https://nanta-data.dev/en/tags/airflow/</link><description>Recent content in Airflow on nanta - Data Engineering</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>© 2026 nanta</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nanta-data.dev/en/tags/airflow/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>BigQuery Data Transfer + Airflow: Why We Create and Delete Transfers Every Batch</title><link>https://nanta-data.dev/en/posts/bigquery-data-transfer-airflow/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nanta-data.dev/en/posts/bigquery-data-transfer-airflow/</guid><description>We built a pipeline to load S3 mart tables into BigQuery using Data Transfer Service. During PoC, DTS scheduling was managed by GCP. For production, we moved it into Airflow — creating a transfer object each batch tick and deleting it after completion. User feedback drove improvements: multi-day lookback windows, concurrent execution quota management via slot pools, and empty source path detection through GCP logging API.</description></item><item><title>Building Iceberg Table Monitoring with Trino Meta-Tables and Prometheus Pushgateway</title><link>https://nanta-data.dev/en/posts/iceberg-table-monitoring/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nanta-data.dev/en/posts/iceberg-table-monitoring/</guid><description>As our Iceberg table count grew, we needed systematic monitoring for file health. We built dashboards using Trino meta-tables, Prometheus Pushgateway, and Grafana to track file counts, sizes, and partition distribution. Along the way we hit Trino bugs and performance issues worth documenting.</description></item><item><title>2026 Data Engineering Trends and Where Large-Scale Platforms Stand</title><link>https://nanta-data.dev/en/posts/2026-data-engineering-trends/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nanta-data.dev/en/posts/2026-data-engineering-trends/</guid><description>Analyzing 2026 data engineering trends from Joe Reis&amp;rsquo;s 1,101-respondent survey, contrasted with our team&amp;rsquo;s current architecture at a large-scale platform. An honest look at what we&amp;rsquo;re doing well and what we need to work on.</description></item><item><title>Airflow 3.0 Migration Guide: Lessons from a Large-Scale DAG Environment</title><link>https://nanta-data.dev/en/posts/airflow-3-migration-guide/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nanta-data.dev/en/posts/airflow-3-migration-guide/</guid><description>Practical lessons from migrating to Airflow 3.x ahead of the 2.x EOL. Covers major breaking changes, a phased upgrade strategy, DAG compatibility approaches, and hard-won lessons from operating hundreds of DAGs in production.</description></item></channel></rss>